<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>LSTM on Vishal Lakha</title>
    <link>https://vishallakha.github.io/tags/lstm/</link>
    <description>Recent content in LSTM on Vishal Lakha</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 14 Feb 2022 22:41:10 +0530</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://vishallakha.github.io/tags/lstm/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Object Detection and OCR</title>
      <link>https://vishallakha.github.io/blog/object_detection_and_ocr/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Feb 2022 22:41:10 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishallakha.github.io/blog/object_detection_and_ocr/</guid>
      <description>Objective Generate automatic Red Light Violation Tickets for Indian License Plate by detecting the License Numbers using Computer Vision.
Description  In this project, I was reading the CCTV feed(Images) of traffic Junctions, and performing the object detection task to identify the license plates for cars, motorcycles, auto rickshaws, trucks etc. I have used Tiny Yolo model as its very fast, lightweight and accurate enough to handle the load efficiently.    Once the license plate region has been identified, the cropped image is passed to the custom trained OCR model to extract out its license number.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Custom Named Entity Recognition Model with Deep Learning</title>
      <link>https://vishallakha.github.io/blog/ner_model/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Jan 2022 23:29:21 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishallakha.github.io/blog/ner_model/</guid>
      <description>Objective Build a NLP model which can extract out the important keywords (related to a particular domain) from documents.
 Description In this project i have trained a custom Named Entity Recognition Model, which takes input of strings (max size 40) and predicts the Named Entities from the text. It used ELMo (Embeddings from Language Models) , bi directional LSTM and a time distributed dense layer.
Technology Stack Python, Keras, Tensorflow, LSTM</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
